<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--

    Copyright (c) 2012, 2018 Oracle and/or its affiliates. All rights reserved.

    This program and the accompanying materials are made available under the
    terms of the Eclipse Distribution License v. 1.0, which is available at
    http://www.eclipse.org/org/documents/edl-v10.php.

    SPDX-License-Identifier: BSD-3-Clause

-->

<!DOCTYPE book [
<!ENTITY % ents SYSTEM "docbook.ent">
%ents;
]>
<section version="5.0"
         xml:id="unmarshalling-unmarshalling-is-not-working-help"
         xml:lang="en" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
         xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
         xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:m="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
    <title>Unmarshalling is not working! Help!</title>

    <para>There are a few common causes for this problem. These causes often
    exhibit similar symptoms:</para>

    <orderedlist>
        <listitem>
            <para>Instance documents are invalid</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
            <para><literal>JAXBContext</literal> is not created correctly.</para>
        </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <section xml:id="Make_sure_your_instance_document_is_valid">
        <title>Make sure your instance document is valid</title>

        <para>First, use an independent schema validator to check if your
        document is really valid with respect to the schema you compiled. When
        the root element of a document is invalid, then the unmarshaller will
        issue "unexpected element" errors. When a portion of a document is
        invalid, JAXB skips that portion, so the end result is that the
        unmarshalling returns normally, yet you notice that a part of the
        content tree is missing. This is often the desirable behavior, but it
        sometimes ends up masking a problem.</para>

        <para>Also, try to install <literal>ValidationEventHandler</literal> on the
        unmarshaller. When a portion of a document is skipped, the
        unmarshaller notifies a <literal>ValidationEventHandler</literal>, so it
        allows you to see what's going on.</para>

        <example>
            <title>Installing ValidationEventHandler</title>

            <programlisting language="java"><![CDATA[Unmarshaller u = ...;
// this implementation is a part of the API and convenient for trouble-shooting,
// as it prints out errors to System.out
u.setEventHandler(new javax.xml.bind.helpers.DefaultValidationEventHandler());

u.unmarshal(new File("foo.xml"));]]></programlisting>
        </example>

        <para>Also consider installing a <literal>Schema</literal> object to the
        unmarshaller, so that the unmarshaller performs a schema validation
        while unmarshalling. Earlier I suggested that you try an independent
        schema validator, but for various reasons (not all tools are reliable,
        you might have made an error and used a different schema/instance),
        using validating unmarshalling is a better way to guarantee the
        validity of your instance document being unmarshalled. Please follow
        the <link
        xlink:href="http://java.sun.com/j2ee/1.4/docs/tutorial/doc/JAXPIntro.html#wp65584">JAXP
        tutorial</link> for more about how to construct a <literal>Schema</literal>
        object from your schema.</para>

        <para>If you are unmarshalling from XML parser APIs (such as DOM, SAX,
        StAX), then also make sure that the parser/DOM is configured with the
        namespace enabled.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="Check_if_your_JAXBContext_is_correct">
        <title>Check if your JAXBContext is correct</title>

        <para>(TODO: This also applies to the marshaller. Think about moving
        it.)</para>

        <para>The other possibility is that <literal>JAXBContext</literal> is not
        set up correctly. <literal>JAXBContext</literal> "knows" a set of classes,
        and if it doesn't know a class that it's supposed to know, then the
        unmarshaller may fail to perform as you expected.</para>

        <para>To verify that you created <literal>JAXBContext</literal> correctly,
        call <literal>JAXBContext.toString()</literal>. It will output the list of
        classes it knows. If a class is not in this list, the unmarshaller
        will never return an instance of that class. Make you see all the
        classes you expect to be returned from the unmarshaller in the list.
        When dealing with a large schema that spans across a large number of
        classes and packages, this is one possible cause of a problem.</para>

        <para>If you noticed that a class is missing, explicitly specify that
        to <literal>JAXBContext.newInstance</literal>. If you are binding classes
        that are generated from XJC, then the easiest way to include all the
        classes is to specify the generated <literal>ObjectFactory</literal>
        class(es).</para>
    </section>
</section>
